Guide to the William Lyon Phelps Papers
Yale University Library
Manuscripts and Archives
William Lyon Phelps papers
1826-1944
1887-1943
MS 578
Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943.
10.5 linear feet
The papers include correspondence, writings, lecture notes, student notebooks, research notes, memorabilia, and scrapbooks of clippings documenting William Lyon Phelps's career as a professor of English and popularizer of literature. Phelps's lecture notes and annotated volumes on English literature comprise half of the papers. The papers also include a small quantity of family papers relating to Phelps's father and wife.
Manuscripts and Archives Sterling Memorial Library 128 Wall Street P.O. Box 208240 New Haven, CT 06520 Web: http://www.library.yale.edu/mssa/ Email: mssa.assist@yale.edu Phone: (203) 432-1735 Fax: (203) 432-7441
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gifts of the estate of William Lyon Phelps, 1943; Thomas S. Brush, 1957. Additional gifts from various donors, 1955-1996. Gift of John J. Burns Library, Boston College, 2004.
Associated Materials
Related material: William Lyon Phelps Papers, (Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University).
Biographical Sketch
William Lyon Phelps was born in New Haven, Connecticut, on January 2, 1865. He received a B.A. degree from Yale in 1887, an A.M. degree from Harvard in 1891, and a Ph.D. from Yale in 1891. Phelps taught English at Yale from 1892 until 1933 and was a popularizer of literature through his public lectures, radio addresses, and syndicated newspaper columns. He died in New Haven on August 21, 1943.
Description of the Papers
The William Lyon Phelps Papers include correspondence, writings, lecture notes, student notebooks, research notes, memorabilia, and scrapbooks of clippings which document Phelps's career as a professor of English at Yale University and his role as a popularizer of literature, public lecturer, and syndicated columnist. Phelps's lecture notes and annotated volumes on English literature comprise half the papers. The papers include only scattered items from Phelps's voluminous correspondence. The larger quantity of correspondence is located in the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library at Yale University. The papers also contain a small quantity of family papers relating to Phelps's father and wife.
The estate of William Lyon Phelps donated a major portion of the Phelps Papers to the Yale University Library in 1943. Thomas S. Brush donated a significant addition to the papers in memory of Katherine B. Ingersoll in 1957. Additional gifts were received from several individuals between 1955 and 1984.
The papers are arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, 1888-1944. II. Research Files, 1889-1936. III. Student Notebooks, 1878-1904. IV. Personal Files, 1883-1943. V. Family Papers, 1826-1930.
Series I contains the bulk of the correspondence in the papers. Most of the letters are incoming and include family letters, Yale announcements, students' correspondence, queries concerning Phelps's research on Robert Browning, and requests from the public relating to Phelps's syndicated newspaper columns. Some items concern Yale faculty and administration. The series also includes architectural plans by Murphy and Dana for Phelps's study, prescriptions for his eyes, printed copies of Phelps's writings, and a transcript with photographs of James S. Ennis, Jr.'s letters to his father during his military service in World War I.
Series II is the largest in the papers. It includes seven boxes of printed volumes annotated with Phelps's notes on the works of several major English authors. The most complete notes are those on the works of Browning. The NOTES section of the series includes Phelps's lecture notes, either for his course lectures or for his public lecture series, along with occasional items of correspondence, clippings, and printed material. Most lecture notes are on specific American, English, or European novelists, playwrights, and poets, but there are also notes on more general literary subjects. The section also includes notebooks from Phelps's research at the British Museum in 1900.
Series III is composed of volumes of notes taken by Phelps during his graduate course work and research at Yale and Harvard and later studies in Germany. The notebooks record course work with Professors Wheeler, Beers, Ladd, Sumner, and Dexter at Yale, and with Professors Baker, Wendel, Royce, Child, Kittredge, and Briggs at Harvard. In addition the series includes notebooks from the Yale University Bible Club under Dr. Sanders, Phelps's 1887 honors thesis on the "Idealism of George Berkeley," notebooks on mathematics from Phelps's high school studies at Hartford Public High School, and Phelps's lecture notes from his year of teaching at the Westminster School.
Series IV includes Phelps's writings, notes, scrapbooks, student papers, and memorabilia. The articles and speeches include typescripts of Phelps's column on books, "Billy Speaks," while folders 233-246 contain mounted clippings in notebooks of Phelps's syndicated newspaper column from 1933 to 1937. Folder 247 contains a copy of Phelps's address as Hartford High School class orator, while folder 250 includes poems written by Phelps. These writings represent a limited sample of Phelps's work. Folder 231 contains additional lecture notes by Phelps and others, while folder 228 is composed of the tributes to Yale honorary degree recipients which were read by Phelps at commencement. Phelps's notes and other research material on Browning are contained in folders 226-227.
The series also includes several one act plays written by students, exam questions and students' exams, and Phelps's gradebooks. In addition the series contains memorabilia of the Metaphysicals such as invitations and parodies for their feast for the sons of John Donne at which Phelps acted as toastmaster. Folder 251 contains a scrapbook of clippings about Phelps, many of them chronicling his activities during summers spent in Huron City, Michigan.
Series V includes a small quantity of family papers, which relate primarily to Sylvanus Dryden Phelps, father of William Lyon Phelps, and to Phelps's wife, Annabel Phelps. The series contains a brief daily diary of Annabel Phelps for January and February 1899. Sylvanus Dryden Phelps's autobography of his life from 1817 to 1839 is in folder 269. Portions of this memoir are transcribed in the biographical sketch in folder 268. Poems by Sylvanus Phelps are included in folder 270. Folder 267 contains an 1841 autograph book of Hannah B.C. Phelps, whose relation to William Lyon Phelps, if any, is unclear. The volume was purchased as a gift for Phelps by a Michigan friend.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series and one addition: I. Correspondence, 1888-1944. II. Research Files, 1889-1936. III. Student Notebooks, 1878-1904. IV. Personal Files, 1883-1943. V. Family Papers, 1826-1930.
Access Terms
Browning, Robert, 1812-1889.; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943.; Yale University. Dept. of English.; Yale University. Faculty.; Yale University. Students.; American literature.; Authors.; Critics.; Educators.; English literature--History and criticism.; Literature--History and criticism.
Collection Contents
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1888-1944; Series I; 0.5 linear feet (1 box)
  This series is arranged in two sections: CHRONOLOGICAL and SELECT.
  - Chronological
    - 1888-1944, no date (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
  - Select
    - Beers, Clifford, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ennis, Jack Seffren, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Twain, Mark, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- RESEARCH FILES, 1889-1936; Series II; 5 linear feet (14 boxes)
  This series is arranged in two sections: ANNOTATED VOLUMES and NOTES.
  - Annotated volumes
    - Browning
      - Vols. 1-6, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
      - Vols. 7-12, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 16-18)
      - Vols. 13-18, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 19-21)
    - Chaucer: vols. 1-6, 1889 (Box 5, Folder 22-24)
    - Milton: vols. 1-2, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Spenser: vol. 1, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Tennyson
      - Vols. 1-4, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 27-28)
      - Vols. 5-10, 1896 (Box 7, Folder 29-31)
      - Vols. 11-12, 1896 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Notes, [ca. 1894-1936] (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - American literature
      - B - H (Box 8, Folder 33-44)
      - H - W (Box 9, Folder 45-59)
        See also: Notes on English literature, box 11, folder 109
    - English literature
      - A - J (Box 10, Folder 60-94)
      - K - She (Box 11, Folder 95-115)
      - Shi - W (Box 12, Folder 116-127)
    - European literature and miscellanea
      - A - M (Box 13, Folder 128-155)
      - Poets: A - Z (Box 14, Folder 156-183)
      - Pu (Box 14, Folder 184)
      - R (Box 14, Folder 185-187)
      - S - T (Box 15, Folder 188-195)
- STUDENT NOTEBOOKS, 1878-1904; Series III; 1.5 linear feet (4 boxes)
  This series is arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Bible study, 1888-1890, no date (Box 16, Folder 196)
  - English drama, 1890-1891 (Box 16, Folder 197)
  - English history, 1889-1890 (Box 16, Folder 198)
  - English literature, 1889-1892 (Box 16, Folder 199-201)
  - English literature, 1890-1892 (Box 17, Folder 202)
  - Germany, 1904 (Box 17, Folder 203-204)
  - Honors thesis, 1887 (Box 17, Folder 205)
  - Mathematics, 1878-1880 (Box 17, Folder 206-207)
  - Philosophy, 1887-1890, no date (Box 18, Folder 208-209)
  - Romanticism, 1890-1891 (Box 18, Folder 210-212)
  - U.S. history, 1887-1889, no date (Box 19, Folder 213-215)
  - Miscellanea, no date (Box 19, Folder 216a)
- PERSONAL FILES, 1883-1943; Series IV; 2.5 linear feet (6 boxes)
  This series is arranged alphabetically by topic or record type.
  - Articles and speeches
    - A - B, 1936 (Box 20, Folder 216b)
    - As I Like It (Box 20, Folder 216c)
    - "Billy Phelps Speaks", 1941-1943, no date (Box 20, Folder 217)
    - C - F, 1917, 1928-1934 (Box 20a, Folder 218)
    - G - I, 1904-1931 (Box 20a, Folder 219)
    - L - N, 1932, no date (Box 20a, Folder 220)
    - O - V, 1938, no date (Box 20a, Folder 221)
    - W - Z, no date (Box 20a, Folder 222)
  - Awards and citations
    See: box 21, folder 230
    See also: box 27
  - Books read, 1919-1942 (Box 20a, Folder 223-224)
  - Books read and reviewed, 1941-1943 (Box 20a, Folder 225)
  - Browning, 1926, 1930, no date (Box 21, Folder 226-227)
  - Commencement speeches: notes, no date (Box 21, Folder 228)
  - Hartford lectures, no date (Box 21, Folder 229)
  - Honorary degrees, awards, and citations, 1891-1942 (Box 21, Folder 230)
  - Lectures and syllabi, 1902, no date (Box 21, Folder 231)
  - Metaphysicals, 1900-1924 (Box 21, Folder 232)
  - Newspaper articles, 1933-1937 (Box 21, Folder 233-234)
  - Newspaper articles, 1933-1937 (Box 22, Folder 235-242)
  - Newspaper articles, 1933-1937, 1940, 1989 (Box 23, Folder 243-246)
  - Notebook: Hartford High School, 1883 (Box 23, Folder 247)
  - Photographs, 1891-1937, no date (Box 23, Folder 248)
  - Plays, 1892-1893, 1934-1935, 1941-1942 (Box 23, Folder 249)
  - Poetry, 1914, 1927 (Box 23, Folder 250)
  - Scrapbook, 1926-1927 (Box 23, Folder 251)
  - Sloan prize, no date (Box 23, Folder 252)
  - Student exams, no date (Box 24, Folder 253)
  - Student exams: forms, 1893-1917 (Box 24, Folder 254)
  - Student grades, 1893-1909 (Box 24, Folder 255-256)
  - Student papers, 1941 (Box 24, Folder 257)
  - Student plays, 1922, no date (Box 24, Folder 258-260)
    See also: Sloan prize, box 23, folder 252
  - Student plays, 1922, 1933, no date (Box 25, Folder 261)
  - Writings of others, 1910-1941, no date (Box 25, Folder 262-263)
  - Yale University: miscellanea, 1906, 1908, no date (Box 25, Folder 264)
  - Miscellanea, 1909-1943, no date (Box 25, Folder 265)
- FAMILY PAPERS, 1826-1930; Series V; 0.5 linear feet (1 box)
  This series is arranged alphabetically by the names of family members.
  - Phelps, Annabel L.: diary, 1899 (Box 26, Folder 266)
  - Phelps, Hannah B. C.: autograph book, 1841 (Box 26, Folder 267)
  - Phelps, Sylvanus Dryden
    - Biographical sketch, no date (Box 26, Folder 268)
    - Memoir, 1894 (Box 26, Folder 269)
    - Poems, 1834-1845 (Box 26, Folder 270)
    - Poems and miscellanea, no date (Box 26, Folder 271)
  - Phelps, William Lyon, II, no date (Box 26, Folder 272)
  - Miscellanea, 1826, 1930 (Box 26, Folder 273)
- OVERSIZE, Series VI
  - Honorary degrees, awards, and citations, 1883-1942 (Box 27)
- Additional Material, Accession 2005-M-042
  - Letter to Albert S. Cook re: poetry, 1918 Oct 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter to "Walter", 1921 Nov 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)